A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Executive Officer Subject Files, Susan Berresford FA1349
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Executive Officer Subject Files, Susan Berresford
1968-1990
Rockefeller Archive Center
Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
Howe, Harold, II (1918-2002)
Ford Foundation
FA1349
3.23 Cubic Feet 9 boxes - 6 letter document containers, 2 legal document containers, and 1 half-letter document container
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the Executive Officer Subject Files of Susan Berresford, including correspondence, project proposals, newsletters, press materials, and other documents from projects and programs overseen by Susan Berresford, many related to Woman's Programs. The majority of materials were created in the late 1970s to early 1980s. During this period, Berresford held many roles at the Foundation, including program assistant and program officer in the Division of National Affairs, officer in charge of Women's Programs, and Vice President for US and International Affairs Programs.
The collection also contains Education and Research Division files of Harold Howe II, a former vice president of the Education and Research Division, that were transferred to Susan Berresford in 1981.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
1. Subject Files, 1968-1990
2. Education and Research Division files of Harold Howe II, 1966-1981
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Ford Foundation in 2017 and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2017:075 and 2017:088
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Susan Berresford served as the first female president of the Ford Foundation from 1996 to 2007. She joined the Foundation in the early 1970s as a program assistant and program officer in the Division of National Affairs. In 1980, Berresford began leading Women's Programs, and she was promoted to Vice President for US and International Affairs Programs in 1981. In 1989, all Ford Foundation programs - domestic and international - were put into one division led by Berresford: Africa and the Middle East (AME, formerly MEA), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA). In 1995, Berresford was chosen as executive vice president and chief operating officer (COO) of the Foundation.
When Susan Berresford became president in 1996, she reorganized the Foundation in to three large program themes that would inform grantmaking in the United States and developing countries: Assets with a focus on poverty, Peace and Social Justice on rights issues, and Education, Media, Arts and Culture to pull together related endeavors. She also created a separate communications program. Each program was led by a vice president. Berresford strongly reinforced the institutional and grantmaking goal of affirmative action.
She maintained significant support, domestically and internationally for women's issues. She endorsed and encouraged the worldwide meetings staff members and grantees to continue to hold joint meetings in order to create a greater sense of partnership and shared purpose. Berresford encouraged the development of local and regional peace and security programs in developing countries.
Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation -- Overseas Offices; Women's programs
- Subject Files, 1968-1990; 1
  - Sex Equity in Education in 1980, Federal Funding to Support (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sears, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Seckler, David - Sukhomajri, A Rural Development Program in India, 1980 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Plant, Morgan - National Coalition Against Domestic Violence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Peru, & Colombia Trip Report S.B. (See Colombia-original), 1980 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Phillips, Barbara Ashley, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Public Policy, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Project Proposal - "Feminist Agendas and Social Services"
  - Prostitution, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Prindle, Deborah, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - President's Advisory Committee on Women, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Powers, Patricia Public Action Coalition on Toys (PACT), 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Seeds, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sex-based Stereotypes, Sex Biases & National Data Systems (2 copies) - U.N. Secretariat, 1980 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sex-Education, 1980 July (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sex Equity Newsletter - Teachers College, Columbia University, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sexual Harassment, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Redirection, Project, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Thompson, Marcia, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    The Cash Reserve Program
  - Quester, George, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Texas Programs for Teen Parents, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - UN World Conference on Women Summarized - Women Today, 1980 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Walls, David - Acting Director, University of Kentucky, 1979 March 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ream, Joyce J. Ream, Hoblitzelle & Associates, 1980 (?) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Redclift, Nanneke, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rio de Janeiro Field Office Material, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Robards, Saide, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - CC: 680 - Requests for Books, Publications, etc., 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Roderick, Tom, 1980 November (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Rodman, Hyman - University of North Carolina, Greensboro, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rowser, Sharon, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ruof, Peter, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Roupp, Richard - Bank Street College of Education, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Sarin, Madhu, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Schachter, Esther R., 1978 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Scholarships, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Waite, Joan - Report, Research on Participation of Black Men in Home & Family Care Resp., 1980 May (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Sommers, Tish - Older Women's Rights Committee, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Soedjatmoko - The Child in Development Planning, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Simmons, Ozzie G., 1981 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Socio-biology, 1980 January 24 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Siegel, Patricia Squires (Patty), 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Shapiro, Stephen A. - Volunteer Counseling Service of Rockland County, Inc. (Domestic Violence), 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Sexton, Patricia, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Pogregin, Letty, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Women's World Banking, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Powell, Douglas - Merrill-Palmer Institute, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Popper Foundation, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Beresford Apartments, 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Romanus, Gabriel, Honorable - Riksdagen, Sweden, 1978 June 1978 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - White, Virginia - Editor, Grants Magazine, 1979 July 23 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Walters, Patricia A. - Lecturer in Sociology, University of Salford, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Wharton, Cynthia L. - Program Administrator, Charles H. Revson Foundation, 1979 March 22 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Wickens, David L., Ed. D. c/o Ken Slate, 1977 October (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Wertheimer, Barbara - Cornell University & Ann Nelson, 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 55-57)
  - Takanishi, Ruby - Report of the Ford Foundation - Examining the Social Structure of Training of Early Childhood Educators, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - White House Conference on Families, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Wilson, Blenda - The Ford Foundation: Possible Future Role for Improving Schools [Draft], 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Schorr, Alvin - Community Service Society, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Schrank, Robert, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Schultz, Victoria, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Schultz, Ted - "Power of Observation", undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Seabrook, Enny Cramer, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - South Africa - Daily Mail - New Urban Rights: Home Crisis Looms, 1980 August 21 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - South Bronx Development Office - South Bronx Regional Demonstration Project for Comprehensive Adolescent Pregnancy Care, Prevention and Parent Programs [DRAFT], 1980 March-June (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Soviet Feminist Exiles - Discussion with Tatiana Mamanova, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Spangenberg, Gail - Memo - Your Thoughts about Higher Education and Disadvantaged People in Cities, 1980 May 28 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Spanish - Cuernavaca Language School, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Staples, Eugene (Rocky) - Funding for Women's Programming Activities, 1980 August-1981 February (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Stein, Susan - Company Cares for Children, The, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Sundar, Pushpa, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Sviridoff, Mitchell, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Annual Report Community Board Program, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Policy - National Policy Exchange, Youth Policy, Center for Policy Studies - Working Papers, 1981 May (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Morgan, Lynn - Policy Versus Practice: The Case of Mexican Health Center, 1979 December (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - "Rouse Proposal" - The Enterprise Foundation, 1981 June 10 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Salamon, Lester M. - The Federal Government and the Nonprofit Sector: Implications of the Reagan Budget Proposals, 1981 May (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Sawhill, Isabel V. - The Employment of "The Program for Economic Recovery", 1981 May 8 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Madrid, Arturo - Assistant Secretary for Educational Research and Improvement - United States Department of Education, 1981 June 10 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Gormbley, Wiliam P. - Guidelines on Discrimination Because of Sex - Sexual Harassment, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Teitelbaum, Michael S. - The City Club of San Diego - In a Spirit of Open Inquiry… Immigration a Time for Decision the National Questions, 1981 June 12 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Annual Report 1980 - Center for Community Change (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Martinez, Vilma S. - Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund (MALDEF), 1981 May 19 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - The New World Foundation (NWF), 1981 June 15 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Project Redirection Site News - Education and Training: Putting Teens on the Right Track, 1981 May (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Joint Center for Political Studies, Inc. - Voting Rights Act, 1981 April 29 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Goodman, Ellen - Anti-Women Economics from a Dippy Misogynist, 1981 June (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Thompson, Marcia - American Writers Congress, 1981 June (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - A. Leon Higginbotham, Jr., 1981 June 1 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Matthew Birmingham - Cushman & Wakefield's Building Security Manager, 1981 June 11 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Taub's Business Employment Foundation's Paper, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 93)
- Education and Research Division Files of Harold Howe II, 1966-1981; 2
  Harold Howe II served as the vice president of the Education and Research Division at the Ford Foundation from 1968-1981. He transferred these files to Susan Berresford upon leaving his position in 1981.
  - Education and Research Division Budgets: FY 1976 - FY 1977, 1975-1981 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Education and Research Division Budgets: FY 1977 - FY 1978, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Education Committee, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Index of Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Education Committee Papers, 1967-1980 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    Education Committee Meetings - all transferred from Harold Howe II VP Files to Susan Berresford VP Files, June, 1981
  - Education and Public Policy Committee Papers, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Education Committee, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Education and Research Division - Budgets: FY 1972, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Education and Research Division Budgets: FY 1971, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 101-102)
    Includes Strategic Budget Issues for FY 1971 and Beyond
  - Education and Research Division Budgets: FY 1970, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 103-104)
  - Education and Research Division Budgets: FY 1969, 1968 June (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Education and Research Division Budgets: FY 1968, 1967 June (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Education and Research Division Budgets: FY 1973, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - Education and Research Division Budgets: FY 1967, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Correspondence - Education Committee, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Division of Education and Research Budget and Special Projects, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Harold Howe II - Agenda - Education Committee, 1973 March 28 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Education Committee Papers, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Education Committee Papers - Proposed Plan for School Desegregation Grants, 1972 December 7 (Box 9, Folder 113)
    For consideration by Education Committee of Ford Foundation Trustees
  - Education Committee Papers, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 114)